Finding Aid for Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action (University of Michigan) publications, 1945-2016
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action (University of Michigan) publications
1945-2016
University of Michigan. Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action.
9770 Bimu B28 2
Publications produced by Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action and affiliated programs. Includes catalogs of professional development courses, pamphlets and manuals describing benefit programs such as health care, disability, and retirement. Also contains personnel manuals; as well as statistics analyzing faculty salaries. Also contains annual salary record of faculty and staff.
10 linear feet
932.7 MB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 7384 ).
Periodic additions to the publications are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The University of Michigan Personnel Office was established in 1945 to develop and implement personnel policies, administer faculty promotion and tenure-granting policies, and negotiate and monitor contracts with unionized university employees. While recommendations for faculty promotions and tenure began in the department, school, or college, the Personnel Office was responsible for conducting them to the president, the provost, and to the Board of Regents for final action. This office also maintained the official employment record for all university faculty and staff. The Personnel Office annually published salary information of all university employees. Researchers will find these listings in the University of Michigan Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action publications group.
In 1972 the University of Michigan created the Affirmative Action Program to develop recruiting practices and set goals and timetables to respond to federal laws passed in the 1960s guaranteeing equal opportunity in employment to women and minorities. The first director of the Affirmative Action Program was Nellie M. Varner. Her chief responsibility was to interpret the specific guidelines of the Department of Education (Title VI, Title IX), the Department of Labor (Title IV and Title VII) and to build a structure within the university to meet these guidelines. In addition she served as a liaison between the university, federal government officials, and the university's Commissions for Minority Affairs and Women, established by President Robben Fleming in 1971. His charge to the commissions was to examine university policies, procedures, and practices which might contribute to discrimination against minority groups and women, and make recommendations. The commissions and the Affirmative Action Program worked together to develop procedures and submitted recommendations to the president to improve various programs within the university.
Reorganized in 1976 the Affirmative Action Program was changed to Affirmative Action Office and the Commissions for Minority Affairs and Women were integrated into the office. The move eliminated duplication of effort and focused activity on the eradication of discriminatory practices. Gwendolyn Baker was appointed the new director of the Affirmative Action Office. In 1978 Charles Allemand replaced her as director of the Affirmative Action Office.
During the 1970s and 1980s, the role of the office grew to include the protection of handicapped individuals, people between the ages of 40 and 70, and veterans of the Vietnam War. In addition, non-discriminatory policies included religion, national origin, height, weight, marital status, and sexual orientation.
In 1980 Virginia Nordby became director of the Affirmative Action Office. The office was divided into compliance and programs teams, reflecting the major functions of the office, to meet federal affirmative action guidelines, and to serve the needs of groups or individuals on campus protected by nondiscrimination laws. Nordby directed both teams.
The compliance team was responsible for the data retrieval, analysis, and writing the reports on minority student recruitment and retention, faculty and staff employment, and affirmative action compliance required by the university and the federal government. In addition, it monitored the race and gender composition of the faculty, staff, and student body; set affirmative action goals and followed their progress, and oversaw faculty and staff recruitment. The program team addressed the needs of members of protected groups through grievance counseling, program development, and policy recommendations. It also provided workshops to the university community.
The Affirmative Action Office also worked with constituency groups, providing direct staff and financial support to such groups as the Academic Women's Caucus, the African-American Organizations Coalition, the Age Concerns Council, the Association of Black Professionals and Administrators, the Commission for Women, the Women of Color Task Force, the Men of Color Task Force, the Task Force on Sexual Orientation, and the Women's Initiative Group.
In 1988 Virginia Nordby left the Affirmative Action Office. Mary Ann Swain became the interim director. In 1989, Zaida I. Giraldo became the director. In 1992, Jimmy A. Myers took over the position as Interim Director.
On February 15, 1994 the Affirmative Action Office combined with the Personnel Office to become the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action. Jackie McClain was appointed as the executive director.
The Publications of the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action measures 10 linear feet and covers the period from 1945 to the present, including material produced by the predecessor organization, Personnel Office. The publications series is divided into three subseries: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications and Topical Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action.; University of Michigan. Personnel Office.; University of Michigan. Office of Faculty and Staff Statistics.; University of Michigan--Employees--Salaries, etc.EmployeesSalaries, etc.; University of Michigan--Faculty--Salaries, etc.Salaries, etc.Faculty; University of Michigan. Benefits Office.; University of Michigan. Human Resource Development.; University of Michigan. Office of Faculty and Staff Statistics.; University of Michigan. Benefits Office.; University of Michigan. Human Resource Development.; Comparative instructional salary data.; University of Michigan faculty and staff record.; University of Michigan. Personnel Office.
Genre Terms:
Statistics.; Manuals.; Pamphlets.
- Unit Publications
  Unit Publications include brochures and manuals created by the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action (and earlier Personnel Office) to assist employees in making decisions regarding health care, disability, and retirement. A variety of reports are also included, among them a 1997 self-assessment, which explains the various offices merged under the broader Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action.
  Although produced by a number of differently titled organizations within and outside of HRAA, the statistical resources included here contain salary and staffing figures and tables. The key publication is the annually published Analysis of Salaries Paid to the Instructional Staff. Based on fall term data, this publication analyzes current salaries of the university's instructional staff by department and within the department by rank. The analysis is complete from 1960 to present. Beginning with the 1989-1990 academic year graduate teaching assistants were included. The analysis lists the number of persons at each rank or level with mean, median, minimum and maximum salaries and their average age. The survey also incorporates the Dearborn and Flint campuses in its analysis. The Office of Faculty and Staff Statistics also publishes Comparative Instructional Salary Data, which compares the salaries of the university's academic departments with those of other universities around the country. This publication is a compilation of data extracted from the Big 10 and AAU data exchanges and surveys conducted by Oklahoma State University and Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The data is based on the fall term and an academic (nine month) year.
  - Annual Reports
    - Employees' Retirement Plan, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Choose Your Own Program: Blue Cross and Blue Shield Benefits, 1961-1973 (Box 1)
    - Faculty and Academic Staff Benefits, 1957-1967 (Box 1)
    - Let Yourself Grow, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946- (Box 1)
    - Your Retirement Annuity, 1957-1969 (Box 1)
    - UMatter Staff Recognition Program, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Workplace Awards, 1994- (Box 1)
  - Flyers regarding AFSCME/UAW election, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Employees' Retirement Plan, 1945-1963 (Box 1)
    - Group Insurance Plans and Programs, 1950-1988 (Box 1)
    - Income Protection for Totally Disabled Staff Members, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Major Medical Expense Plan, 1962-1973 (Box 1)
    - Travel (includes Information on Reimbursement and Insurance), 1963 (Box 1)
    - You and Your Job at the University of Michigan, 1950-1969 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - HRAA News (print-outs of e-mail), 2000-2004; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Inter-action Quarterly Newsletter of Human Resources/ Affirmative Action, [issue 1 vol 1; issue 2, vol 1-3; issue 5, vol 2; issue 6, vol 3; issue 7; vol 4], 1995-1997 (Box 1)
  - Regulations
    - Vacation and Sick Leave, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Availability Assessment (labor market availability), 1976; 1978 (Box 1)
    - Building Blocks for Performance Planning and Appraisal, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Business Process Reengineering Human Resources Pathways HRM Service Delivery System and Recommendations Survey, May 1997 (Box 1)
    - The Culture and Climate for Quality: Perceptions of the Work Environment of the University of Michigan, 1994 (Box 1)
    - 1997 Benefits Survey, University of Michigan, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Retirement Benefits Provided by TIAA-CREF to Emeriti Professors, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Self-Assessment, August 1999 (Box 1)
    - Viewpoints and Attitudes: Report of a Survey Among University of Michigan Staff Members, undated (Box 1)
  - Salary Analysis
    - An Analysis of the Salaries Paid to the Faculty of the University of Michigan [Office of the Vice President and Dean of Faculties] (Box 2)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 2)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - An Analysis of the Salaries Paid to the Teaching Staff of the University of Michigan 1962-1963 [Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs] (Box 2)
    - An Analysis of the Salaries Paid to the Teaching Staff of the University of Michigan [Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs]
      - 1962-1963, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1964, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - 1964-1965, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1966, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - An Analysis of the Salaries Paid to the University of Michigan Teaching Staff [Office of Academic Affairs]
      - 1966-1967, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - An Analysis of Salaries Paid to the University of Michigan Teaching Staff [Office of Academic Affairs]
      - 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - An Analysis of Salaries Paid to the University of Michigan Teaching Staff [Office of Institutional Research; Office of Academic Affairs]
      - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - An Analysis of Salaries Paid to the University of Michigan Instructional Staff [Office of Academic Affairs]
      - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
        (main volume and summary volume)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 2)
        (summary volume only)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 2)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - An Analysis of Salaries Paid To the University Of Michigan Instructional Staff and Graduate Student Teaching Assistants [Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs - Personnel]
      - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 3)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 3)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - An Analysis of Salaries Paid To the University Of Michigan Instructional Staff and Graduate Student Instructors [Human Resources Records and Information Services; Human Resources Information Service]
      - 1996-1997 (Box 3)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 3)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 3)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 3)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 3)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 3)
      - 2002-2003 (Box 3)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 3)
      - 2004-2005 (Box 3)
      - 2005-2006 (Box 3)
      - 2006-2007 (Box 3)
      - 2007-2008 (Box 3)
    - An Analysis of Salaries Paid To the University Of Michigan Regular Instructional Faculty, Regular Clinical Instructional Faculty, Lecturers and Graduate Student Instructors
      - 2009-2010, .ZIP
      - 2010-2011, .PDF
      - 2011/12-2012/13, .PDF
  - Statistics
    - Executive Salary Information Executive Officers, Deans and Directors, July 1992 (Box 4)
    - FTE Reports
      - 1987 (Box 4)
      - 1991 (Box 4)
      - 1993 (Box 4)
      - 2008, .ZIP
      - 2009, .ZIP
      - 2010, .ZIP
      - 2011, .ZIP
      - 2012, .ZIP
    - Faculty Merit Increase Program
      - 1989-90 (Box 4)
      - 1990-91 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Salary Increase Program
      - 1991-92 (Box 4)
      - 1993-94 (Box 4)
      - 1994-95 (Box 4)
      - 1995-96 (Box 4)
      - 1996-97 (Box 4)
      - 1997-98 (Box 4)
        (Academic Administrative, Primary, and Faculty Salary Adjustment Report)
    - Comparative Instructional Salary Data
      - 1986-87, 2 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1987-88 (Box 4)
      - 1988-89 (Box 4)
      - 1989-90 (Box 4)
      - 1990-91 (Box 4)
      - 1991-92 (Box 4)
      - 1992-93 (Box 4)
    - Integrated Postsecondary Education Data System (IPEDS) Reports
      - Ann Arbor Campus Faculty Demographics, 2008; .ZIP
      - Summary
        - 1999, .ZIP
        - 2000, .ZIP
        - 2001, .ZIP
        - 2002, .ZIP
        - 2003, .ZIP
        - 2004, .ZIP
        - 2005, .ZIP
        - 2006, .ZIP
        - 2007, .ZIP
        - 2008, .ZIP
        - 2009, .ZIP
        - 2010, .ZIP
        - 2011, .ZIP
        - 2012, .ZIP
    - Some Comparisons of Salaries Paid to the Faculties of the Nine State-Supported Institutions of the Western Conference (Big 10) 1956-57 and 1961-62 (Compensation of Academic Personnel Report Series), 1962 (Box 4)
    - Teaching Salaries Compared, 1956-1957 to 1963-1964 (Big 10 Universities and UC-Berkeley)
    - University of Michigan and Big Ten Schools Instructional Staff Salary Comparison by Department, 1983-1984; 1984
  - Statistics
    - Executive Salary Information Executive Officers, Deans and Directors, July 1992 (Box 4)
    - FTE Reports
      - 1987 (Box 4)
      - 1991 (Box 4)
      - 1993 (Box 4)
      - 2008, .ZIP
      - 2009, .ZIP
      - 2010, .ZIP
      - 2011, .ZIP
      - 2012, .ZIP
    - Faculty Merit Increase Program
      - 1989-90 (Box 4)
      - 1990-91 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Salary Increase Program
      - 1991-92 (Box 4)
      - 1993-94 (Box 4)
      - 1994-95 (Box 4)
      - 1995-96 (Box 4)
      - 1996-97 (Box 4)
      - 1997-98 (Box 4)
    - Comparative Instructional Salary Data
      - 1986-87, 2 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1987-88 (Box 4)
      - 1988-89 (Box 4)
      - 1989-90 (Box 4)
      - 1990-91 (Box 4)
      - 1991-92 (Box 4)
      - 1992-93 (Box 4)
    - Integrated Postsecondary Education Data System (IPEDS) Reports
      - Ann Arbor Campus Faculty Demographics, 2008; .ZIP
      - Summary
        - 1999, .ZIP
        - 2000, .ZIP
        - 2001, .ZIP
        - 2002, .ZIP
        - 2003, .ZIP
        - 2004, .ZIP
        - 2005, .ZIP
        - 2006, .ZIP
        - 2007, .ZIP
        - 2008, .ZIP
        - 2009, .ZIP
        - 2010, .ZIP
        - 2011, .ZIP
        - 2012, .ZIP
    - Some Comparisons of Salaries Paid to the Faculties of the Nine State-Supported Institutions of the Western Conference (Big 10) 1956-57 and 1961-62 (Compensation of Academic Personnel Report Series), 1962 (Box 4)
    - Teaching Salaries Compared, 1956-1957 to 1963-1964 (Big 10 Universities and UC-Berkeley) (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan and Big Ten Schools Instructional Staff Salary Comparison by Department, 1983-1984; 1984 (Box 4)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  Sub-Unit Publications consist of materials produced by units within the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action. These include the Benefits Office and Human Resource Development. Benefit Office Material includes a variety of brochures, flyers, and catalogs designed to help employees understand and choose benefits. Material begins in 1954 and continues to the present. Human Resource Development publications include course catalogs of professional development offerings for university employees. The catalogs begin in 1979 and continue to the present (with some gaps, particularly for 1985 and 1986.
  - Benefits Office
    - Brochures, Flyers, and Benefit Catalogs (includes staff orientation and open enrollment) (Box 5)
      - 1954-2004 (Box 5)
  - Human Resources Development
    - Brochures and Flyers (Box 6)
    - Programs and Services Catalogs (Professional Development)
      - 1979-1984 (Box 6)
      - 1987- (Box 6)
- Topical Publications
  Topical Publications consist of annual salary lists. These are computer printouts and digital files that are prepared and made available by the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action in compliance with the Michigan Freedom of Information Act. They are arranged chronologically by academic year, beginning with 1979/80. Data within a given year is arranged alphabetically by employee name. Data available includes employee name, appointment title, appointing department, annual appointment period, full time pay rate, and appointment fraction. For some years the employee's date of original hire is also included. For the years 1979/80 to 1985/86 information exists only for faculty or university employees classified as professional/administrative. Subsequent lists include all university employees regardless of job classification. The printed salary lists from 2002/03 to 2008/09 have been scanned as PDF files. Beginning in 2009/10 the print copy was discontinued.
  The most recent salary list is added to the collection as it becomes available. Salary information for years prior to 1979/80 can be found in the records of the University of Michigan Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer.
  - Salary Listings
    - 1979/80-1987/88, 9 folders (Box 7)
    - 1988/89-1995/96, 8 folders (Box 8)
    - 1996/97 (Box 9)
    - 1997/98 (Box 9)
    - 1998/99 (Box 9)
    - 1999-2000 (Box 9)
    - 2000/01 (Box 9)
    - 2001/02 (Box 9)
    - 2002/03, .PDF (Box 9)
    - 2003/04, .PDF (Box 10)
    - 2004/05, .PDF (Box 10)
    - 2005/06, .PDF (Box 10)
    - 2006/07, .PDF (Box 10)
    - 2007/08, .PDF (Box 10)
    - 2008/09, .PDF (Box 10)
    - 2009/10, .PDF
    - 2010/11, .PDF
    - 2011/12, .PDF
    - 2012/13, .PDF
    - 2013/14, .PDF
    - 2014/15, .PDF
    - 2015/16, .PDF